- Hi, I'm Matthew Feickert.
I'm a particle physicist and I'm a postdoc
at the University of
Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
where I work on the ATLAS experiment
as well as for the Institute
for Research and Innovation
in Software for High Energy Physics.
And today I'll be talking
to you about pyhf.
Which is a pure Python
statistical fitting library
from the high energy physics community
that leverages both
tensor library backends
as well as automatic differentiation.
Okay, so before we go any further
I first want to take this opportunity
to introduce the pyhf
core development team.
So we're Lukas Heinrich,
who is a postdoc at CERN,
I already introduced myself,
I am Matthew Feickert,
a postdoc at the University of
Illinois at Urbana Champaign,
and then also Giordon Stark
who is a postdoc at the University
of California Santa Cruz.
We're all experimental high
energy particle physicists
that work together on an
experimental collaboration
with 3,000 of our closest
colleagues called ATLAS
that's located just outside of
beautiful Geneva Switzerland
at CERN's Large Hadron Collider, the LHC.
Here you can see the obligatory picture
of the LHC's huge 27
kilometer circumference
drawn over the Swiss French countryside
with markers indicating where
the main experiments reside
along the ring about
100 meters below ground.
And our collaboration is formed around
the ATLAS detector itself, seen
here with a T-Rex for scale,
which you can think of as a
cathedral-sized digital camera
for recording the events of
colliding beams of protons
from the LHC at almost the speed of light
for us to then later analyze.
The reason that we're
smashing protons together
at extreme energy densities
and looking at the splattered
remains in our detector
is because we want to understand
the fundamental forces of the universe,
like electromagnetism
and the strong and weak nuclear forces,
and their interactions
with the most elementary
particles of matter.
With a long history of success,
we have been able to distill down
what we know about the universe so far
so that with a little bit of manipulation
you can fit it in one equation
on the side of a coffee cup,
but we know that's not the full picture.
We're still trying to understand
some of the physics we do know about
like the Higgs boson we found in 2012,
as well as see if we can
find evidence for new physics
like dark matter.
So we're trying to ask the universe
pretty fundamental
questions about what it is,
but the universe isn't interested
in answering them too easily.
We have to run our colliders
for years at a time
producing millions of
collisions per second
to try and collect as much
high-quality data as possible,
on the rare events that
can give us a glimpse
as to the missing parts of our picture.
When we do analyze all that data,
we're looking to extract
as much information as possible out of it.
We're using it to search for new physics
like when we discovered a
particle that was consistent
with the theoretical predictions
of the Higgs boson in 2012.
But we're also using it to
make precision measurements
of the physics we do know about
to better understand its properties.
So that when we don't find evidence
of new physics in our searches
we can still provide the
best limit constraints
on different possible theories.
All of this requires
building statistical models
and then fitting those models to the data
to perform statistical inference.
However, the model complexity
for some of these analyses
can be huge, resulting in the
time to perform these fits
being many hours.
This is obviously a problem
and we want to try and empower analysts,
which are ourselves,
with fast fits and expressive models
so that we can decrease the
time to inference and insight.
We turn now to HistFactory,
one of the most extensively
used statistical models
in all of high energy physics.
This flexible probability
density function template
was first developed in the
field as part of the efforts
in the search for the Higgs boson.
Since the discovery of the Higgs,
it's gone on to be used ubiquitously
in both measurements of
known physics processes,
that is physics that is described
by what we call the Standard Model,
as well as searches for new physics,
which we refer to as being
beyond the Standard Model.
When we breakdown what the
HistFactory template is though,
we see it has a simple form.
Though here we do need to
introduce some terminology.
The terms "channel" and "sample."
Here, a channel just means
a particular selection
criteria for the analysis.
If you'll allow me to simplify
to avoid giving an aside lightning talk
on the Standard Model,
this might mean requiring
seeing two particles of one type
and a third of another in the detector,
and that their combined energy
lies within a specific range.
So, in the plot below,
we see that each bin is a
different analysis region,
a different channel.
Here there's just one bin in each channel,
but that's just this particular example.
There are analyses in which
channels contain many bins.
So following that,
a sample corresponds to a
particular physics process
that could result in producing particles
that would get selected
for a particular channel.
So, each of these colored histograms
in the histogram stacks in each bin
corresponds to a different sample.
So as you can see, some samples
--- physics processes ---
show up in different channels.
Okay, given this aside,
we can backtrack to see that
the HistFactory template
is just comprised of a main part, in blue,
which is the product of
Poisson distributions
across all bins and all channels.
Where the event rate
parameter for the Poisson
is determined from the nominal event rate
that is affected by
different multiplicative
and additive modifiers in each sample.
The reason for using Poissons
is that we're doing counting experiments
for subatomic processes
that are inherently random.
The second part, in red,
is comprised of constraint p.d.f.s
that allow for different
auxiliary measurements
to constrain the overall model
and encode different
systematic uncertainties
from the physics theory
and the detector responses.
So, in this example plot,
the samples could share
a systematic uncertainty
in the normalization in
addition to other modifiers.
This gives us a mathematical grammar
to setup a simultaneous fit
for multiple channels, regions,
each with multiple bins and
multiple samples, processes,
that are all coupled to
a set of constraints.
But the important part is
that this is just mathematics.
No software specification
is defined anywhere,
but until very recently in 2018,
the only implementation
that existed of HistFactory
was in the monolithic
C++ library called ROOT
that has been the computational backbone
of experimental high energy
physics for almost 25 years.
The change was the creation of pyhf,
the first pure Python
implementation of HistFactory,
which as you can see below,
is just a pip install away on PyPI
and openly developed on GitHub.
Okay, now that we've hopefully motivated
the existence of pyhf and
the HistFactory formalism,
let's dive into the pyhf API a bit.
The basic object that is
at the heart of everything
is, unsurprisingly, the model.
However, what we're interested
in doing with the model
is going to be maximum likelihood fits.
So we'll be dealing a lot with the logpdf
as we want to get the log
likelihood of the model parameters
conditioned on the observed data.
In this minimal simple example,
using just two bins and a single channel,
we see that we can create
a simplistic model quickly
and then with the data from
our experimental obervations
and the model auxiliary constraints,
we can get the log likelihood
of the default initialization
parameters of the model.
If we look at how this model
is actually being represented
internally though,
we see that it is a
directed computational graph
that shows the full
formalism of HistFactory.
Each node of the graph
represents a vectorized
n-dimensional array,
or, as we'll call it, "tensor" operation.
You can see from these colored nodes
that the data and the model parameters
enter at different points,
and are additionally largely
factorized into subgraphs.
These parameter and data graphs
combine again at the bottom of the graph
to be used in the computation
of the final log likelihood.
Okay, we can now turn our
attention to the core task
of performing maximum
likelihood fits with pyhf.
Here, we want to minimize
the objective function
which is twice the
negative log likelihood,
as minimizing the negative log likelihood
will result in maximizing the likelihood.
We can see that the pyhf API
for this is pretty transparent.
And looking at the same
minimal examples before,
we see that performing
the maximum likelihood fit
with our optional
return_fitted_val keyword argument
returns the maximum likelihood estimate
of the model parameters
as well as minus 2
times the log likelihood
at these best fit parameters.
Additionally, we can
see in these final steps
that we perform a demonstration
check of that explicitly.
We're now going to use our tools
to get at what we really care about,
performing a profile likelihood fit
for our parameter of interest μ.
Here we profile out the
nuisance parameters theta
by expressing the nuisance parameters
as functions of the
parameter of interest itself.
So, from a physics standpoint,
the parameter of interest
is typically the normalization factor
on the count of the new physics process
we're searching for.
And since we're searching for it
we call it the "signal",
and the Standard Model physics
we call the "background".
So we would call this
particular parameter of interest
the signal strength.
Okay, anyway,
so what we want to do for
this profile likelihood fit
is on the top line, perform
a constrained best fit
for a given signal strength value µ
that we're testing
to get the best fit nuisance parameters
given this test value.
And then compare that result
to the unconstrained
best fit on the bottom
where all the model parameters
are free parameters in the fit.
So we're doing a hypothesis test
for the production rate
of our new physics.
So, we can then take this
result as a test statistic
and calculate a modified
p-value that we call the CLs,
using either results from
asymptotic distributions
or generating pseudoexperiments.
And this is all to ask,
given our model and the data,
did we discover new physics?
And we want to do all of
this as fast as possible.
And that's a lot, but pyhf
provides a hypothesis test API,
and so continuing in our minimal example,
we see that performing the hypothesis test
for a signal strength
that would be consistent
with theory predictions, one,
and our return_expected_set
keyword argument,
we get back both the
observed modified p-values
as well as a band of variations
from the expected result
if there was no new physics.
This is exactly what we need.
As the serialization of the likelihood
had previously been in a
domain-specific binary format
that provided some difficulties
for analysis reinterpretation,
we gave a lot of thought to
how pyhf should do things.
This resulted in the decision
to create a JSON schema
that would allow for a
declarative specification
of the HistFactory model.
On the right, we see a
short working example
of the JSON spec
for a single channel, two
bin counting experiment
with a systematic uncertainty,
ignoring of course the
highlighted comments,
which I put in by hand and
are obviously invalid JSON.
Okay, so given our coverage
of the HistFactory formalism,
we see that we have a list of channels
within a...
with a list of samples
with an associated list of rate factors
and systematic uncertainties,
as well as the observed data,
our declared parameter of interest,
and the schema version.
So all of HistFactory is represented here,
so we have a declarative,
full serialization of the likelihood.
JSON provides us many advantages.
It is both human and machine readable,
making it mentally much
easier to deal with,
additionally, JSON is an industry standard
and will probably be with us
until the heat death of the universe.
So we have long, long-term
support baked in.
In the same vein,
it is parsable in pretty
much every language,
so if alternative implementations exist,
our models can be easily ported.
Finally, given the large
cost of running the LHC
and building experimental
detectors the size of buildings,
we want to try and reuse analyses
as much as possible in the future.
JSON is plain text and so versionable,
easily preserved, and highly compressible,
making it a great choice.
Another great thing about using JSON
is that we then also get JSON Patch,
which allows us to
easily mutate our models.
If we take the example
JSON spec we just looked at
and use the pyhf command line API
to perform a CLs computation,
we get an observed value
given the background and
signal models considered.
We can call this using signal model A.
If we want to now test
some new physics model,
we can call that signal model B,
that would have different contributions,
then we can use JSON Patch
to patch in this new signal on the fly
and recompute our result.
So we now see that the
observed modified p-value,
the observed CLs that we get
for this new patched-in signal model
is different from the
original signal model result.
In a typical physics analysis,
we additionally want to
evaluate signal hypotheses
for a range of possible particle masses,
which results in hundreds of points
in our parameter space to evaluate.
The choice of JSON allows for
us to further simplify things
by breaking out the
background-only model JSON
into one file and then
creating a patch set file
that contains all of the
signal model JSON patches
inside of it.
These two JSON files,
along with the pyhf schema,
fully preserve the analysis likelihood
making it reusable by both theorists
and experimentalists alike.
These full likelihoods
can then be publicly published to HEPData,
a repository for data
associated with particle physics results,
which will even mint a DOI for
these data products as well.
When validating that the
results obtained with pyhf
were consistent with the
results from the C++ library,
we saw excellent agreement.
On the right plot, made with Matplotlib,
there are actually
multiple contours overlaid,
not just one with cross hatching.
But the agreement between the C++ results
and pyhf is so good
it's very difficult to see any deviations.
As an additional really nice aspect,
when we computed all the points required
to construct this contour,
pyhf was able to do so
significantly faster,
taking minutes as compared to hours.
The publication of the
full likelihoods to HEPData
using the pyhf schema, has
an additional distinction
of solving a nearly 20 year-old problem
in the field of particle physics.
At a workshop in 2000,
whose proceedings the
quotes here are taken from,
there was agreement in the community
that the LHC experiments should
publish their likelihoods
as part of the results.
However, the technical aspect
of what exactly to publish
and how, are non-trivial.
By focusing on just HistFactory models,
given their extensive use and popularity,
we were able to make
good on this agreement
when in 2019 the ATLAS
collaboration published to HEPData
the likelihoods for a search
for bottom-squark pair
production in final states
contain Higgs bosons, b-jets,
and missing transverse momentum.
The speed-ups we observed with
pyhf, on a single machine,
can be further improved
by parallelizing the fits
of all the signal hypotheses.
Here we see a GIF on the
right of the Jupyter Notebook
that is sending out fits of the models
for all the signal hypotheses
to run on 25 worker nodes in the cloud,
and then updating the exclusion
contour plot in real time
as those fit results come back in.
As the different fits are
independent of each other,
the patch background and signal models
can be sent out to worker nodes on demand,
taking advantage of the
scaling to make quick work
of this embarrassingly
parralelizable problem.
Through this weak parallelism,
the same contour plot we just saw
can be fully reproduced
in just three minutes.
This clearly motivates the
idea of "fitting as a service"
on clusters in the future.
The reason for pyhf's performance
comes from the choice to
use tensor algebra libraries
as our computational backends.
Our default backend,
as you may have noticed
from the examples so far,
is NumPy with SciPy
providing the optimizer.
We additionally also support
PyTorch, TensorFlow, and JAX
as computational backends
with full feature parity.
One of the motivations
for choosing machine learning
frameworks as backends
is to exploit automatic differentiation
of their computational graphs
and the hardware acceleration on GPUs
that they are designed to
work with to speed up fits.
As can be seen here in
the lower left plot,
in this preliminary study
of the effects of hardware
acceleration on pyhf fit times
for admittedly somewhat
unrealistic models,
we see that as the model complexity grows
there is significant gains
in the speed-ups provided by GPUs.
In some cases, even an order of magnitude.
This has allowed for some real models
to move from being fit
in hours to minutes,
and minutes to seconds.
Turning overnight jobs into
nearly interactive analyses,
or at least an excuse to go for a coffee.
Additionally, while we'd like to think
good things about ourselves,
physicists are not professional
software engineers,
nor the incredible NumPy
and SciPy dev teams.
We're physicists!
So, being able to build
on top of the hard work
of the professionals that build
these open source libraries
is hugely empowering.
What pyhf provides is a unified API
to our computational backends
through our tensorlib shim.
You can see here for our
four supported backends,
the code needed for pyhf
to provide a Normal distribution object
through our tensorlib normal_dist API.
Without the analyst ever needing to care
which backend they've chosen to use.
This additionally allows
for transparently changing the backend
with our set_backend API.
In this example, we see
that using pyhf's API
we were able to build
two Normal distributions,
and then evaluate their log pdf
for particular observation values
in the native tensor
representation of each backend.
All of course giving consistent values.
Additionally, for the
tensor library backends
that provide automatic differentiation,
we gain access to the full
gradient of the likelihood
resulting in our accuracy being limited
by floating point precision.
We can exploit the full gradient
by providing it to the modern optimizers
our backends provide to
help speed up the fit.
It is also worth pointing out
that this was made possible
by the fact that the backends
are constructing computational
graphs of our model,
as we saw before, and then
applying the chain rule
to the tensorized
operations in these graphs
to move the gradients through the graphs
along with the data.
The benefits that are received
from these tensorized representations
are not to be understated.
The ability to represent
the HistFactory models
in this graph visually
alone is impressive.
When for comparison, this
is the graph of the model
used in the Higgs discovery
in the C++ framework.
Zooming out to have it all fit on screen
makes it difficult to even see
the nodes of the operations.
I think this serves as
a good visual example
of the wins that we get from
moving computational complexity
into tensor dimensionality.
pyhf is already starting to be
used in physics publications
in the high energy physics community.
What is exciting is that both theorists
and experimentalists are using it.
On the left you can see
a phenomenology paper
that used pyhf for
performing reinterpretation
with the GIF below cycling
through different physics models.
And on the right, you
can see the public note
that ATLAS released on the
use of public full likelihoods
for reproduction of results.
Below that is the CERN
news article headline
that was published on
open full likelihoods
highlighting what a dramatic
change it has allowed.
We'd also like to think
that the uses of pyhf
are not only found inside
of high energy physics.
Here, we see public data
from the Fermi Large Area Telescope
analyzed with pyhf in a Jupyter Notebook.
The LAT is a high-energy
gamma-ray telescope
on the Fermi gamma-ray
space telescope spacecraft
used to observe gamma-ray photons
coming from extreme cosmological events.
We can represent the
photon count in the LAT
as a binned model,
such that after
constructing a model in pyhf
and performing a maximum likelihood fit,
the results can be visualized with healpy.
Here, we can view the resulting mapping
as a two-dimensional histogram
with special binning choices.
While none of the pyhf core
dev team works in astrophysics,
we're interested to see
what overlaps might exist
for use of pyhf.
In summary, pyhf is a statistical library
that provides accelerated fitting
for high energy physics models
by exploiting tensor libraries
as computational backends
for vectorized operations,
automatic differentiation,
and hardware acceleration.
It uses a JSON schema to
provide a flexible specification
for declarative models,
and through JSON Patch
is an enabling technology
for reinterpretation of physics results.
pyhf is also at the heart of
the growing Pythonic ecosystem
in high energy physics.
So let me plug the talks
of my Scikit-HEP and IRIS-HEP colleagues,
Jim and Henry, who are
both giving talks this week
in the high performance Python track.
Go check them out as
they're going to be great!
Also feel free to ask us any questions
about Scikit-HEP or IRIS-HEP.
Thank you so much for
listening to my talk.
Here I'll note that pyhf
is a Scikit-HEP project
and that I received support from IRIS-HEP
to help develop it.
But I've just been so excited
to get to talk with you at SciPy this year
and I can say on behalf of
Lukas, Giordon, and myself
that we would love to get to
talk with you more about pyhf.
So, please come talk to us
and I'm looking forward
to the Q&A tomorrow.
Finally, I wanted to say thank you
to the SciPy conference organizers
for making this conference
happen at all this year,
and for making this
conference be a success.
You've done a heroic job
and I wanted to say thanks
for giving me an opportunity
to get to share our work with everyone.
Hope everyone has a great
rest of the conference.